[Music]
hey everyone so I think we're both a
little bit nervous about this but we're
going to go there we're going to go into
conspiracy theories even just saying
that word I know that some people react
to it because they're say that's just a
way of dismissing alternative narratives
so we're not going to do that we're
going to really talk about it in the
context of the crisis that we're going
through right now the thing that we're
really interested in is why the levels
of certainty on all sides it was really
interesting we put out a film yesterday
or a couple of days ago Daniel SHM Acton
Berger about conspiracies and I saw one
of the first comments was which side is
Daniel on and then five minutes later oh
I'll keep watching he's on it's like
this is really interesting but we can't
make sense of things if we've got kind
of an attachment to one side or the
other so what we're going to do in this
film is talk to some of the people that
we've had on the channel before and some
new people so john vivace who's a
cognitive scientist and professor of
psychology at toronto who looks at like
how the brain works why we fixate on
certain things and ignore other things
like how our pattern recognition works
we're losing a lot of our connections
we're losing a lot of our identity
around work or our home what we consider
our home and where we're safe is
shrinking and then at the same time
we're beginning when it from our are
like even our scientific and political
authorities we're being told about this
thing which is like an Old Testament
deity it's ubiquitous it's invisible
you don't know where and when it's gonna
strike you don't know who to trust
anymore
and look what it's demanding from us
it's demanding very strict strict purity
codes it's like we're suddenly back in
you know the early Iron Age and that is
that you know and and this is deeply
baked into us this way of thinking
purity codes and demonic forces and also
to Carl Miller who is a researcher at
demos in the UK has been looking at
information warfare and
spirity theory since about 2010 so you
tweeted out something like hey my friend
is basically a sane individual never
been into conspiracy theories before but
now won't shut up about you name it 5g
co vid miracle cure George Soros so is
the your sense that this this stuff is
growing right now yeah I mean as a
researcher you always want to you always
want to say things that you only have
robust empirical evidence for and we're
still doing the research on it but yeah
I think I think the the evidence is now
mounting that this is the single most
pregnant moment for conspiracy theories
probably in history and also will play
some clips from Daniel smacked and
Berger who we've had on the channel
before a lot of people have a strong
bias towards wanting certainty
recognizing how big of an infinity the
unknowable is everyone has to make very
deep friends with uncertainty to not be
mentally ill that doesn't mean that they
have to do the move that all there is is
uncertainty nothing can possibly be
known which is also gibberish because
the fact that I can't know anything with
perfect certainty doesn't mean that I
can't know things with much higher
relative certainty I think the more
we've been talking about this over the
last few days with a lot quite a lot of
energy because it's ramping up so much
the more it's felt like something
something that guests like in the
Gilchrist's have said in the channel and
that we've said a lot as well which is
that very often it's not the water it's
the how and so what feels important
right now to me in this information
ecology which is just mad crazy there's
narrative there's narrative warfare
there's narratives flying around
everywhere there's information there's
misinformation it's it's sometimes
impossible to tell I think the question
we should be asking is how do we arrive
at truth not what truth should we be
arriving at I think part of what's
important is for individuals to start
having you know first all too hot start
having our own discernment because the
old gatekeepers of our information are
no longer reliable it means we have
personal responsibility
well I don't see a lot of right now on
any side of let's say what Peter
Lindbergh is called the liminal war
that's happening the big information
warfare is a an admission of uncertainty
it almost seems like this desperate
anxious urge to get away from
uncertainty at any cost
so it's either there are no conspiracies
you're all mad or there are conspiracies
and this is what they definitely are so
that in between space isn't I think a
wishy-washy space it's it's the most
realistic space to try and navigate but
much much harder there's another really
good framing piece I think from one of
the people we featured on the channel
quite a lot Jordan Hall where he talks
about that in the process while we're
moving from like broadcast to
decentralized media we're moving from
effectively a sort of TV world where
there's a kind of eternal that there's a
very short memory that the main feature
of the Internet and the of the digital
media landscape we're in a world of kind
of eternal memory and in a world of
eternal memory it's a completely
different dynamic where it's possible to
piece things together how many people
used to know about actual conspiracies
that definitely happened Operation
Paperclip Mockingbird like what was on
COINTELPRO MKULTRA like things that
actually happened before the internet
the number of people that knew about
those was probably pretty small it's
almost like a cliche now they're sort of
like the great revealing or the great
unveiling like there is clearly some
truth in that there are things that
people have been doing that are going to
be uncovered and that there are now
paper trails like it's much more
difficult to hide your tracks completely
in so many different areas so there are
things that happened and that we're in a
completely different landscape but then
you've got this also idea of like
overactive pattern recognition or
reading too much in which also happened
with John Vevey key we'll talk about
really well it jives with a lot of very
good cognitive science so Whitson
Jennifer Whitson has done great
experimental work showing the following
and think about how this this just links
up with everything I'm saying
if you put people in situations where
they feel that they're losing control
now she did very careful work to show
it's not just that there's a threat
people if people have a threat and they
feel that they can respond what what I'm
gonna talk about doesn't happen but if
people feel that they're losing control
and you induce this in them you know
very experimentally then what will
happen is they will tend they will be
much more prone to seeing the losery
patterns so if you give them noisy data
they'll see faces in the data and
they'll find patterns and and now
directly she directly tested that when
people are in those situations they are
much more prone to believe in conspiracy
theories as well so what people are
doing is it looks like right loss of
control and then what the brain does is
ah find a pattern find a pattern find a
pattern find a part of make meaning
because if you make meaning especially a
meaning that in which you play some role
right like you have an important role
you're the pure and there's the impure
right then that will presumably afford
the brain at least a pretense of being
able to interact and start to regain
control over its environment now that's
really really interesting because that
also lines up with a lot of work about
you know hyper with that we can we that
we have an evolutionary predisposition
to what's called hyperactive agency
detection so the idea is that when in in
our evolutionary background the
detecting agents was really important
because you're trying to avoid being you
know something something something's
food you're trying to find food you're
trying to find human beings because they
might be dangerous they might be helpful
and so we're wired to overlook the over
and compensate and we miss identify
faces and presences and spirits
everywhere and so once again if you're
starting to look for meaning
right and this hyperactive agency
detectors cook kicking in people are
gonna start positing hidden agencies
behind things and that of course is the
kind of thinking that loads you up for
conspiracy theories and and this also
jives with another thing like when we're
so
the left in the right hemispheres
remember that wonderful conversation I
had with you and McGilchrist right and
the left hemisphere is very you know
certainty and step-by-step and precision
and Andean has a lot of legitimate
criticisms about being that too oriented
but if you remember he did acknowledge
there's a dark side to the right
hemisphere and here's where it is that
right hemisphere probably originally
evolved for predation so it has wide
open you know attention it tolerates
ambiguity it's looking for threat and
it's Gestalt it's grabbing at whatever
patterns it can so when we feel like
we're being preyed upon the right
hemisphere gets very active and it
starts looking for hidden patterns you
see how all of these different adaptive
features are all kicking in and then we
have a cultural milieu and in an actual
biological situation that is triggering
a lot of this you know like I say
mythopoetic thinking an ancient kind of
biblical grammar and so I've been really
concerned that you know this is a way in
which the meaning crisis right because
of the way it's left people my enlarged
very secularized very autodidactic and
fragmented in their spirituality and
then in their religious education and in
their wisdom training that you know that
this stuff is gonna be triggered it's
gonna come up and they're not gonna be
able to monitor and manage it and so
conspiracy theories are going to be
highly highly prevalent the brain
prefers prediction over anything else
right explanation so what happens is
people get very focused on ah this is
this insight explains it all that makes
sense and give me gives me how I can
deal with this and how I can translate
my anxiety into fear and who's the hated
object and who's the villain and what
they do is that become super salient and
then they forget to counterbalance that
with yes but did my was my theory
generated by a lot of good independent
lines of evidence and this is the
hallmark of irrationality we get over
fixated on how much we like the product
of our cognition and we don't pay any
attention to the processing by which
that emerged and David that is
especially dangerous with mythopoetic
thought because we don't know where that
thinking emerges and it comes out of the
yes and we don't track it and presents
itself as numinous to us it's especially
dangerous of this kind of plausibility
bullshitting that we are that we are
liable to I think something that's worth
bearing in mind right now in the
situation we're in in this crisis is
that we're not in normal state as a
culture let's say we're in some kind of
strange altered state and that has a
huge psychological impact and so I have
a background in the psychedelic world
and that is really a and oh and also
other practices and many many of those
practices are about experiencing an
altered state and there's a specific way
to navigate an altered state as well and
what standards have growth describes
psychedelics as is nonspecific
amplifiers which means that whatever's
there already when you have it to have a
psychedelic experience it's there and
amplified massively right so what we're
going through and this is a point
Katherine MacLean has made really well
is that what all the things that were in
our culture and in us as individuals are
suddenly amplified and that means that
we're suddenly faced with a situation
where we have to deal with a lot that's
coming up Katherine MacLean made the
point really well that is like this is
actually a time for us to look at all
that stuff as is coming up it's sort of
a time for facing our demons and our
deepest hopes and fears in fact Zac
Stein who we had on recently made a very
similar point if we're in a kind of
space between worlds and what that means
is that all of our imagined all of our
like imaginal as you could say all of
our imaginal potential the things that
we can imagine is heightened really
really heightened that plays in a lot to
to the kind of ideas and the kind of
possibilities that we can entertain and
that's a that's something that happens
during crises very often and maybe it's
even adaptive because we need new
solutions so there's a natural urge to
consider things we've never considered
before
so that really fits with something that
Jules Evans the philosopher an author
wrote where he looked at kind of the
communities that he's part of like the
sort of spiritual alternative
communities and seen kind of how a lot
of sense making had been breaking down
and came up this really good I thought a
really good analogy between
the two different ways of looking at the
world and there is some research that
people who are prone to conspiracy
theories score high in a personality
trait called schizo typing which is
basically you're you're you're prone to
unusual beliefs and people who are drawn
spirituality also score high in skits a
type II so so those are some of the kind
of possible personality trait overlaps
but I also thought that in a way
spirituality and conspiracy theories
come from a similar kind of historical
culture and that culture is like the
occult late 19th century early 20th
century and occult which grew up and
appeared at a similar kind of time to
now a time of breakdown in certainties
breakdown in traditional authorities and
the time when a lot of people were dying
because of the First World War and it
was a time a liminal time with all kinds
of new ideas and roads including ideas
around like the occult and what you see
in the occult is I guess you could think
of it as two different traditions or two
different experiences one is a kind of
positive conspiracy which you could
define by a kind of sort of mystical
experience like everything is connected
I am connected to everything in the
universe and that's wonderful the
universe's mission is flowing through me
I am naturally attracting helpers to to
kind of bring this new age this glorious
new age for humanity into existence so
you see lots of people in the occult in
this kind of ecstatic of globalism I
call that people like HG Wells or like
Theosophists or you know in the in the
New Age movement in the 70s and 80s
there was a book by Marilyn Ferguson
called the Aquarian conspiracy HG Wells
wrote a book called the open conspiracy
and then these were like ecstatic
networked
bolused progressive free love people and
they're like this is happening an age of
love is happening it's happening through
us we are the we are the kind of
Vanguard we are the elite okay so that's
one what I call the positive conspiracy
and then there's the negative conspiracy
which kind of grew up in reaction to
that and the negative it's kind of like
the bad trip version of that good trip
and it's like everything is connected
there's an elite controlling everything
but I'm not included I'm an outsider to
it so instead everything is connected
and controlled by some shadowy elite of
self-appointed kind of masters and and
and they're all kind of networked
together in their own like think tanks
and organizations and they're
controlling everything and they must be
stalked and it's interesting that what
you see in conspiracy theorists like
Alex Jones say is they're really gunning
for this kind of globalist dailies and
for example Alex Jones in 2010 came out
a conspiracy theory that Bill Gates was
only putting money into vaccines to try
and lower the world population that it
was a eugenics plan what's funny is that
you know looking at the other kind of
tradition of ecstatic globalists a lot
of them were into eugenics like you know
HG Wells Tejada Sharda Julian Huxley
they were eugenicist so I guess what I
think is that these these two traditions
the positive ecstatic euphoric globalist
conspiracy and the negative paranoid
anti-globalist conspiracy they they're
kind of two sides of the same coin
they're the two aspects of a similar
trip they're both prone to magical
thinking they both see everything is
connected
they both they're both ego distortions
in a way in one of the ecstatic trip
your ego is connected to everything and
you are superpower
in the Paranoid trip you are connected
to everything but you are at the mercy
of these of these kind of superpowers
and it's interesting you talk about kind
of a good trip and the bad trip and in
the david icke interview on london real
he actually had both of those sections
he had the kind of the beginning like
the globalist the secret elite that a
room in the world is evil cult and then
at the end very much sort of New Age my
level of consciousness is bigger than
theirs is we all need to kind of realize
that we are God that we are copy of
consciousness those two things existing
together at the same time in the space
of like two hours yeah I think they come
from a similar state of consciousness
which is liminal archetypal magical
mystical I have you if you want to be
you know psychiatric speech schizotypal
but I don't necessarily mean that's a
bad thing but you can see that someone
can switch in in you know on
psychedelics within the same trip even
within the same hour from the kind of
ecstatic euphoric
I am the universe I am I am a super
being to kind of curled up in the corner
in the fetal position they are coming to
get me they being whoever the FBI the
Illuminati so and and there is that
fluidity in these kinds of luminal
States I think it's interesting to think
of it as a trip what you know and it's a
trip in the sense of the normal
boundaries of the ego are distorted
either you're completely expanded to
connect to everything or you're like you
know a shrunken feeling under attack
from invisible forces so what are the
tools can help that can help us in it in
a trip or in a spiritual emergency
they're things like you know reality
checking which of course is hard when
you're tripping
I think humility being you know like
humble including epistemological
humility like being humble about your
truth claims about what you know what
what you what you know
and also being humble about you know
you're probably not a master of the
universe
Jules mentions actually in his piece
this film that came out recently that's
had I think at the time of recording
this was like almost 9 million views on
YouTube called out of shadows which is
looking at primarily how in their view
Hollywood is controlled by the CIA and
kind of there's a big focus that they
have on kind of satanic and occult
influences and I think it's what Jules
is talking about really late explains
very well you know he talks about like
the good good trip of one with
everything and everything is
interconnected to the bad trip of
everything's interconnected only I can
see it and it's all evil or or much of
it is evil there's this huge focus in
that film around evil and actually evil
in the philosophical kind of sets like
the problem of evil of like deep satanic
kind of evil there's a lot of archetypal
the concerns that they have and there's
also to draw on you know what John
Rivera talks about this kind of
hyperactive salience network so they're
talking about various symbols being
satanic I mean this stuff is not new
this has been around the internet for
quite a while but I think it's really
worth picking out you know not the what
are there those conspiracies going on
are there unexplained things yes surely
there are some unexplained things and so
I don't it's not so much about the what
it's about the how what are the
psychological processes and the tropes
and the similarities that we see when
when we talk about the idea that they're
symbols hidden everywhere and a kind of
heightened psychotic state or a
heightened hyper salient state and there
are a lot of similarities and those are
I think really worth bearing in mind I
also spoke to Kyle Miller who hasn't
been on the channel before but had a
really good conversation with him he
works at the place called chasm which is
the Center for the analysis of social
media so really looking at kind of
online sub communities the narratives
that are going on there where they come
from and actually started by looking at
sort of spend a long time in different
sort of conspiracy communities since
about 2010 we're trying to understand
kind of the shift spread of it try and
understand the different communities
involved the different messages which
are contained in it of course trying to
understand the effect is having on
people I mean I I guess like driven by a
concern that at least some conspiracy
theorizing can have kind of direct harms
to people in different ways of course
like this a concern that when you don't
think that coronavirus is a virus but
you think is caused by 5g which is kind
of one of the kind of major claims which
we're seeing emerging and evolve the
moment
well then public health advice looks
very different rather than it being a
kind of series of necessary kind of
clinical steps which are needed to keep
people safe you've suddenly got a smoke
screen being spread by the kind of
medico Politico at apparatus in order to
kind of cover the rollout of a dangerous
technology we're seeing a lot of kind of
miracle cures being sold on on
conspiracy theory groups as well so
there's specific harms we think there
are attached to conspiracy theory
communities that we're trying to try and
understand and then work out ways of
responding to but yeah I mean just in
general like the kind of scale of this
it's absolutely crazy we're seeing
millions upon millions upon millions of
shares across Facebook and Instagram and
YouTube and Twitter that's not even
taking into account the old tech space
where a lot of these things are brewing
in the first place there are flourishing
infrastructures of subreddits which are
kind of impinging on the kind of main
coronavirus reddit's it's a kind of
dizzying the wildering moment where
conspiracy theories have kind of gone
into overdrive
um I'm not just in scale I think the
other kind of really kind of powerful
effect which we're seeing happen in
front of our eyes is it almost it's kind
of emergence of like a kind of Franken
conspiracy theory a kind of meta sizing
of of different and I think it's
actually just an acceleration of what's
happening before the pandemic but but
different kind of groups of conspiracy
theories kind of beginning to kind of
congeal and join together into this kind
of grand broad that profound kind of
series of allegations about how the
world really works and not surprising at
all
because I mean the whole point of
conspiracy theories the reason they
exist and the reason they're created is
because of the joining dots so all you
need to do is join more dots link more
hidden motives identify more hidden
groups and then suddenly kind of bridges
can quite easily be built between
conspiracy theories which initially
started very far apart from each other
mmm yeah and what's your sense cuz I'm
very I'm concerned about that the
narrative usually from kind of
mainstream organs is how could anyone
possibly believe in this and very
dismissive which I think I mean I find
that quite concerning because I think a
lot of people are suspicious of that and
so how like my sense is that actually
that the weak point in this is the level
of conviction that people tend to bring
to it but actually the place to address
it from is a place of more uncertainty
like roundel uncertainty because a lot
of it seems to have this kind of
religious fervor and then I do think
there are some holes in a lot of
mainstream narratives at time so by
saying no you've just got to trust the
mainstream isn't there a danger there
yes there's a lot of problems which
simply reacting to this as as the
product of a series of crackpots firstly
like this sheer scale of this these are
not just a few crackpots these are
millions of our fellow Britons across
the country the idea that people and
have to be kind of crazy or not to
believe in conspiracy theories is the
second problem you know this is kind of
pathologizing it and trying to turn it
into a mental illness which kind of
obviously sits kind of Foursquare
against the general kind of like urging
that we all have on each other which is
the kind of be skeptical independently
minded systems and that we always need
that within a democratic society and
also that there is a in a world that's
so unequal that we're talking about kind
of the 1% and the point of 1% in some
ways metaphorically it seems true that
your life has beyond your control it's
being organized by people who have an
enormous amount of power so to actually
kind of turn that into a narrative about
the world is not that far off how it
feels to be in
usually unequal society in a way no and
I think actually the best explanation
that I've ever come across for
conspiracy theorizing is that it is a a
ideological response to structure
inequality and I think that very clearly
when you look at where conspiracy
theories bloom they bloom in inequality
inequalities of information and of power
societies which are more unequal and
tend to be much less resilient to
conspiracy theories than ones which are
more equal so yeah I mean but I think in
many ways then like what conspiracy
theory actually is is like the
personification of a more generalized
sense that there are agencies and and
and powers in one's life which one kind
of control which is a very human
response but of course in some in many
cases a flawed one - there's a few
things that are becoming kind of
viscerally clear to people right now one
of which is that there does seem to be a
similarity between the spread of the
virus and the spread of kind of viral
misinformation and that sort of it
definitely feels similar and also this
sense that we're all publishers
I suddenly I think people are realizing
we all have and somehow in some sense I
think we all need to learn some
discernment we all need to learn do I
share this do I check this out like
we're all publishers now like every
everyone is is a vector of potential
transmission of misinformation to
someone else right I mean it's it's no
accident that we've long used
epidemiological metaphors in trying to
understand the Internet yeah virality
being that the best one but but
definitely the idea that both
information and behavior infectious you
know and they spread across networks and
we are vectors these are all these are
all ideas which kind of academic studies
have long use to understand how the
internet really works and as as
publishers you know I mean and this is
something that I guess we we called
foreign demos in 2012 but but could
never really managed to quite get on the
National Curriculum
and we do have kind of digital
citizenship requirements we have
responsibilities to one another and
which and again probably now more than
never are easier to forget that we've
got and are easier to ignore you know
it's exactly moments like this when
we're kind of acting really fast you
know we are acting quite impulsively
online and we're probably spending more
time online than we've had in we've had
in the past we're probably living in
environment online which are quite
unfamiliar to us and these are exactly
the moments when we can find ourselves
kind of spreading information to each
other which actually if we were to pause
and consider for a moment and we
probably regard as being harmful but
very interesting ly you know much as
lots of people have been kind of
contacting me to talk about a relative
or a friend that suddenly taken this
kind of conspiratorial leap
they've come they kind of like as I talk
to them about it there's another thing
which is very interesting which becomes
clear which is that when they're
challenged on the information there's
that there's a common response which is
I don't know if it's true or not I just
thought it was and worth sharing you
know the idea that there's more harm in
not sharing a possible pieces to
information than there is in carrying a
possible and piece of bad information
and that's a very very common response
which lots of people have lots of people
have sent to me which I think like it's
probably a massive misconception with
how information works and what
information can do information is not
simply liberating it can also itself
control and harm people and probably the
biggest flick there's one kind of
suggestion I would happen to me as well
as to everyone else because I'm by no
means a perfect representative of this
but we need to kind of view information
diet as being a kind of diet it has
health consequences to us it changes who
we are and where we spend our attention
changes who we think we are the
identities we have the relationships
that we have and we need to use it much
much more self-consciously interpret
deliberately as we go about our
increasingly online lives this is one of
the things that I find with regard to
conspiracy is I find that people have an
aesthetic bias where anything they hear
as a conspiracy they either just kind of
reject it up
right tinfoil hat conspiracy
theorists they just automatically
without studying it even though history
shows how much people have conspired
just meaning some people share info with
each other to advance shared agendas
without sharing it with the public and
sharing some disinfo you can go back to
sunsoo and read about this info and how
to do dis info right like we've been
doing that for a thousand years pretty
intelligently and coordinated lis and so
it's interesting how easy it is for
people to reject something as oh that's
dumb conspiracy thinking when you
actually study history then on the other
hand there are people who if they hear
any conspiracy they assume it's probably
true and if they hear that anything came
from a authoritative institution they
assume it's probably corrupt and that's
also completely silly because if the
groups were that corrupt they would be
overturned so I see that same weird
certainty on both the conspiracy
theorist and the anti conspiracy
theorists like there's this in-group
thing where one is it would be so bad
for my in-group if I was part of the
critical thinking anti conspiracy camp
and I started saying you know maybe
there really is such and such that
there's pretty strong incentives other
than just clear thinking against it see
a real focus for both Carl and John was
that it's a mistake almost I'd like take
on the beliefs themselves it's not
really about that it's about how we come
to those beliefs in the first place I
mean what I see from a lot of the
mainstream organs like the media is like
how can these people possibly believe
this this is just ridiculous and that
just seems very young compassionate
that's not how you would react to
someone in your family who was who was
deluded so how do we how do we engage
with people it's not only
uncompassionate I'm going to be harsher
David it's stupid because it's it's to
maintain the very wrong framing it's to
point at the product and say bad product
bad product bad product Oh bad product
and and not acknowledge the power of
this adaptive machinery there's a reason
why people are making use of this
because it's a it's
maladaptive it's this powerful adapter
machinery and just yelling at them first
of all gets them even more strongly
focused on the product and diverts them
from possibly paying attention to the
process so it just exacerbates things
then secondly its itself it's
disingenuous because it's not paying
attention to the reality of the power of
this adaptive machinery and it's
engaging with what's called a
fundamental attribution error instead of
paying attention to the process in the
context you're just saying oh what a
stupid person right and that is not the
appropriate thing to do
so in fact I would suggest not
challenging people directly under
conspiracy I would say can you get them
involved with other practices that
trigger that same adaptive rewarding
machinery but in a healthy manner that
orient them like the Stoics did towards
the meaning making process this is why
I'm offering the meditations right I'm
gonna go out and challenged you know you
know 5g is causing you know the
coronavirus because you can't when
people are locked into that parasitic
processing it takes a law a very complex
interaction but instead if I can say
well you know you're under stress and I
this sounds like I'm conning them but
it's it's I'm trying to be responsible
like you understood come over here and
learn to meditate and learn to
contemplate and maybe learn to get into
the flow state with doing some Tai Chi
and notice how these things orient you
towards your processing and then take a
deeper and then people start to get
other kinds of insights that can compete
with the conspiracy insights and their
insights of meaning making rather than
maladaptive meaning projection I think
that's what you have to do but I think
so it's kind of a meta move of how do I
come to these conclusions in the first
place after paying attention to what's
going on and how what the processes of
coming to these conclusions but don't
directly point people there right
because if you just say turn around and
look at your processing they're gonna
burn right that's not gonna work so what
you have to do is get them a trap you
have to this is what I talked about this
this is the aesthetics you have to
beautify for them you have to make
beautiful for them paying attention to
the process reflecting on how they're
coming to their
insights and finding insights of
meaning-making as opposed to just
insights of control valuable and
beautiful and tasty to the mind that's
what I'm talking about
so is your sense that the things are
going to get worse before they get
better
Oh like I was saying I think that you
know on the heels of the kool-aid crisis
there is a meaning mental health crisis
of tzunami perforce proportions coming
because you know because what's
happening to people is you know the
relationships are being destroyed their
identities are being challenged you know
their their patterns and routines the
ways they sort of kept themselves busy
are being disrupted in and and they are
they're getting a very clear sense that
things aren't going to go back the old
normal right so their worldview the sort
of the obvious nosov common sense has
been significantly challenged so yeah I
think I think that we're gonna face like
the meaning crisis the mental health
crisis on meth and that's coming and
it's already I've already noticed it so
I have no scientific data I can't
collect it right now right but
anecdotally you know in the network
people are starting to report this this
sort of looming sense of not quite
having the a confident grip on you know
reality things people are saying this a
lot everything feels surreal right I'm
hearing that a law this feels surreal
and that's not said like pleasantly like
a daughter like some sort of Dali
painting is the glue
you know nightmarish surreal and and and
and they're talking about that they're
also you know a kind of nebulous dread
and those are very foreboding for
warnings that you know people's mental
health is gonna be challenged in very
powerful ways yeah and you I think
you're right that we're gonna see more
and more of this kind of thinking
because it feels a lot like the when you
read about accounts of plague times in
London and that was a real
trigger for religious mania for various
different kinds of conspiracy theories
of all kinds of and Leslie happened oh
sorry go ahead I'm just saying yeah that
just if that's in the post I think yeah
I mean I look what happened look I mean
I do I go I go into detail on this in my
series right about what happens to the
entire world view after the Black Plague
right at how it shatters the medieval
synthesis and it just like everything
gets changed and it just launches the
culture in a totally different direction
we are I think now I don't know if
kovetz at the same level as the Black
Plague I'm not I'm not claiming that and
but I think it's reasonable to believe
the following that this is not the only
pandemic we're going to be facing and
the idea that if we can just get through
this and then thing with Google we'll go
back together you know the way they used
to be for centuries and centuries I
think that's really irrational all of
the factors that are the plausible
explanation for why this pandemic
occurred are all in place still and are
all accelerating and so the idea that
this is going to be a one-time affair
I'm very I I find that a very doubtful
proposition yes let's finish on a high
note
but but remember what I said in the
midst of starvation and plague and
literal military siege you have Socrates
and Plato and the birth of an entire new
way of understanding reality that took
the axial revolution throughout the
world so there is right Kairos always
has both of the potentialities available
to us and it is a sensitive period it's
a period unlike most of our lives where
our actions have the capacity our
individual actions have the capacity to
make a significant difference
rebel wisdom was set up to make sense of
the world at a deeper level than the
mainstream media it was built for these
times of crisis and change which is why
we want to do what we can to meet the
challenge of the times more films and
also for our rebel wisdom members weekly
sense-making calls with our amazing
interviewees and also we're introducing
the wisdom gym a place to practice some
of the skills that we've talked about on
the channel thanks for watching and see
you soon
[Music]